<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="c_configuration">
   <title>JBoss Messaging Clustering Configuration</title>
   <para>JBoss Messaging clustering should work out of the box in most cases
   with no configuration changes. It is however crucial that every node is
   assigned a unique server id.</para>
<para>
<warning><para>For a clustered installation it is mandatory that a
                 shared database is available to all nodes in the cluster.
                 The default JBoss AS uses HSQLDB for its database which is a
                 local shared database. Therefore in order to use clustering
                 you must replace this with a different shared database. If
                  the database is not replaced then clustering will not
                  work.</para></warning>
             </para>
 <para>If you want to run multiple JBoss Messaging nodes on the
               same box using the same IP address, e.g. for development
               purposes, then you can use the ServiceBindingManager to do this
               as follows:</para>
               <itemizedlist>
                  <listitem>
                     <para>Uncomment binding manager service from
                     $JBOSS_CONFIG/conf/jboss-service.xml</para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                     <para>Specify the desired port range (e.g. ports-01,
                     ports-02... etc)</para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                     <para>Look at
                     $JBOSS_HOME/docs/examples/binding-manager/sample-bindings.xml.
                     On each port range, JBoss Remoting configuration should
                     look like:</para>
                     <programlisting>
      &lt;service-config name="jboss.messaging:service=Connector,transport=bisocket"
                      delegateClass="org.jboss.services.binding.AttributeMappingDelegate"&gt;
         &lt;delegate-config&gt;
            &lt;attribute name="Configuration"&gt;&lt;![CDATA[
	   &lt;config&gt;
            &lt;invoker transport="bisocket"&gt;
               &lt;attribute name="marshaller" isParam="true"&gt;
                  org.jboss.jms.wireformat.JMSWireFormat
               &lt;/attribute&gt;
               &lt;attribute name="unmarshaller" isParam="true"&gt;
                  org.jboss.jms.wireformat.JMSWireFormat
               &lt;/attribute&gt;
               &lt;attribute name="dataType" isParam="true"&gt;jms&lt;/attribute&gt;
               &lt;attribute name="socket.check_connection" isParam="true"&gt;false&lt;/attribute&gt;
               &lt;attribute name="timeout" isParam="true"&gt;0&lt;/attribute&gt;
               &lt;attribute name="serverBindAddress"&gt;${jboss.bind.address}&lt;/attribute&gt;
               &lt;attribute name="serverBindPort"&gt;4657&lt;/attribute&gt;
               &lt;attribute name="leasePeriod"&gt;10000&lt;/attribute&gt;
               &lt;attribute name="clientSocketClass" isParam="true"&gt;
                  org.jboss.jms.client.remoting.ClientSocketWrapper
               &lt;/attribute&gt;
               &lt;attribute name="serverSocketClass"&gt;
                  org.jboss.jms.server.remoting.ServerSocketWrapper
               &lt;/attribute&gt;
               &lt;attribute name="numberOfRetries" isParam="true"&gt;1&lt;/attribute&gt;
               &lt;attribute name="numberOfCallRetries" isParam="true"&gt;1&lt;/attribute&gt;
               &lt;attribute name="clientMaxPoolSize" isParam="true"&gt;50&lt;/attribute&gt;
            &lt;/invoker&gt;
            &lt;handlers&gt;
               &lt;handler subsystem="JMS"&gt;
                  org.jboss.jms.server.remoting.JMSServerInvocationHandler
               &lt;/handler&gt;
            &lt;/handlers&gt;
         &lt;/config&gt;
            ]]&gt;&lt;/attribute&gt;
         &lt;/delegate-config&gt;
         &lt;binding port="4657"/&gt;
      &lt;/service-config&gt;
              
              </programlisting>
                     <warning><para>You must ensure that the config (like above) is
                     identical to that in
                     <literal>remoting-bisocket-service.xml</literal> With the
                     exception of the actual serverBindPort which clearly must
                     be different for each ports range. Please note that the
                     default JBoss Messaging service binding manager bindings
                     in <literal>sample-bindings.xml</literal> shipped with
                     JBAS 4.2.0 is out of date and you will need to copy the
                     config from
                     <literal>remoting-bisocket-service.xml</literal></para></warning>
                     <para>You should ensure that each node is configured to
                     use a different ports range.</para>
                  </listitem>
</itemizedlist>
  <section id="c_conf.serverpeerid">
	   <title>Unique server peer id</title>
	    <para>Every node deployed must have a unique id, including those in a
		 particular LAN cluster, and also those only linked by message
		 bridges.</para>
<para><note><para>
		Ensure the <literal>ServerPeerID</literal> MBean attribute value in <filename>messaging-service.xml</filename> is unique for each node on the cluster. The <literal>ServerPeerID</literal> value must be a valid integer.
</para></note></para>

   </section>
     
   <section id="c_conf.clustereddests">   
	<title>Clustered destinations</title>
	<para>JBoss Messaging clusters JMS queues and topics transparently across
		the cluster. Messages sent to a distributed queue or topic on one node are
		consumable on other nodes. To designate that a particular destination is
		clustered simply set the clustered attribute in the destination deployment
		descriptor to true.</para>
	<para>JBoss Messaging balances messages between nodes, catering for faster
		or slower consumers to efficiently balance processing load across the
		cluster.</para>
	<para>If you do not want message redistribution between nodes, but still want to retain the other charactereristics
	of clustered destinations. You can do this by not specifying the attribute ClusterPullConnectionFactoryName on the server peer
        </para>
   </section>
   
      <section id="c_conf.clustereddursubs">
	   	<title>Clustered durable subs</title>
	   	<para>JBoss Messaging durable subscriptions can also be clustered. This
		   	means multiple subscribers can consume from the same durable subscription
		   	from different nodes of the cluster. A durable subscription will be
		   	clustered if it's topic is clustered</para>
	      </section>
      
      <section id="c_conf.clusteredtempdest">
	   	<title>Clustered temporary destinations</title>
	   	<para>JBoss Messaging also supports clustered temporary topics and queues.
		   	All temporary topics and queues will be clustered if the post office is
		   	clustered</para>
	      </section>
   
      <section id="c_conf.nonclusteredserver">  
	   	<title>Non clustered servers</title>
	   	<para>If you don't want your nodes to participate in a cluster, or only
		   	have one non clustered server you can set the clustered attribute on the
		   	postoffice to false</para>
	      </section>
      
      
      <section id="c_conf.orderingincluster">
	   	<title>Message ordering in the cluster</title>
	   	<para>If you wish to apply strict JMS ordering to messages, such that a
		   	particular JMS consumer consumes messages in the same order as they were
		   	produced by a particular producer, you can set the DefaultPreserveOrdering
		   	attribute in the server peer to true. By default this is false. The
		   	sideeffect of setting this to true is that messages cannot be distributed
		   	as freely around the cluster</para>
	      </section>
   
   	   
      <section id="c_conf.idempotentops">	
	   	<title>Idempotent operations</title>
	   	<para>If the call to send a persistent message to a persistent destination
		   	returns successfully with no exception, then you can be sure that the
		   	message was persisted. However if the call doesn't return successfully e.g.
		   	if an exception is thrown, then you *can't be sure the message wasn't
		   	persisted*. Since the failure might have occurred after persisting the
		   	message but before writing the response to the caller. This is a common
		   	attribute of any RPC type call: You can't tell by the call not returning
		   	that the call didn't actually succeed. Whether it's a web services call, an
		   	HTTP get request, an ejb invocation the same applies. The trick is to code
		   	your application so your operations are *idempotent*  i.e. they can be
		   	repeated without getting the system into an inconsistent state. With a
		   	message system you can do this on the application level, by checking for
		   	duplicate messages, and discarding them if they arrive. Duplicate checking
		   	is a very powerful technique that can remove the need for XA transactions
		   	in many cases.</para>
			<para>In the clustered case, JBM is by default configured to automatically detect duplicate messages.</para>
	      </section>
      
      
      <section id="c_conf.clusteredcfs">
	   	<title>Clustered connection factories</title>
	   	<para>If the supportsLoadBalancing attribute of the connection factory is set to true then consecutive create connection attempts will round robin between available servers. The first node to try is chosen randomly</para>
	   	<para>If the supportsFailover attribute of the connection factory is set to true then automatic failover is enabled.
		   	This will automatically failover from one server to another, transparently to the user, in case of failure.</para>
	           <para>If automatic failover is not required or you wish to do manual failover (JBoss MQ style) this can be set to false, and you can supply a standard JMS ExceptionListener on the connection which will be called in case of
		   	connection failure. You would then need to manually close the connection, lookup a new connection factory from
		   	HA JNDI and recreate the connection.</para>
	   	
   </section>
</chapter>