<chapter id="about">

   <title>Introducing JBoss Messaging Release 1.2.0.GA</title>

   <para>
       JBoss Messaging is a high performance JMS provider in the JBoss Enterprise Middleware Stack
       (JEMS). It is a complete rewrite of JBossMQ, which is the current default JMS provider in
       JBoss AS 4.0.x series and JBoss AS 4.2.0.GA JBoss Messaging will be the default JMS provider in
       JBoss AS 4.2.x series, probably starting with 4.2.1, and it is already the default provider
       in JBoss 5.0.0.Beta.
   </para>
   
   <para>
      JBoss Messaging will also be part of the JBoss Enterprise Application Platform and the SOA platform, probably from 4.2.1 onwards
   <para>
   
   <para>
      JBoss Messaging is an integral part of Red Hat's strategy for messaging.
   </para>

   <para>JBoss Messaging will also be the default JMS provider for JBoss ESB.</para>

   <para>
       Compared with JBossMQ, JBoss Messaging offers vastly improved performance in both single node
       and clustered environments.
       Please see
       <ulink url="http://wiki.jboss.org/wiki/Wiki.jsp?page=JBossMessagingPerformanceResultsPre1_0">this wiki page</ulink>
       for performance benchmarks and <xref linkend="performance"/> on how to generate your own
       performance benchmarks. JBoss Messaging also features a much better modular architecture that
       will allow us to add more features in the future.
   </para>

   <para>
       While JBoss Messaging only becomes the default JMS provider from JBoss AS 4.2.1 and JBoss 5.0,
       production users on JBoss AS 4.0.x can still take advantage of the performance improvements
       by easily replacing the JBossMQ module with JBoss Messaging.
   </para>
   
   <para><warn>From release 1.3.0.GA onwards JBoss Messaging is designed for JBoss 4.2.x only.</warn></para>
   
   <para>
       The procedure of swapping JMS providers is presented in detail in this manual.
       In <xref linkend="installation"/> we discuss how to install and use JBoss Messaging in
       JBoss 4.0.x production servers. We cover JBoss Messaging-specific configuration options,
       as well as how to run the build-in sanity / performance tests.
   </para>

   <para>
      This guide is work in progress, as new features will be added to the 1.2 baseline at a very
      quick pace. Please send your suggestions or comments to the
      <ulink url="http://www.jboss.org/index.html?module=bb&amp;op=viewforum&amp;f=238">JBoss Messaging user forum</ulink>.
   </para>

   <para>
      <emphasis role="bold">Team:</emphasis>
   </para>

   <para>
      Tim Fox, Project Lead
   </para>

   <para>
      Tim Fox, Technical Lead

   </para>

   <para>
       Clebert Suconic, Core Developer
   </para>
   
   <para>
       Sergey Koshcheyev, Core Developer
   </para>

   <para>
      Other contributions by: Adrian Brock, Bela Ban, Alex Fu, Luc Texier, Aaron Walker,
      Rajdeep Dua, Madhusudhan Konda, Juha Lindfors and Ron Sigal.
   </para>

   <para>
       This manual was written with help from Luc Texier, Lead Support EMEA and
       Sam Griffith Jr., JBoss Documentation Team.
   </para>


</chapter>
