<chapter id="about">

   <title>Introducing JBoss Messaging Release 1.3.0.GA</title>

   <para>
       JBoss Messaging is a high performance JMS provider in the JBoss Enterprise Middleware Stack
       (JEMS). It is a complete rewrite of JBossMQ, the legacy JBoss JMS provider.
   </para>
   <para>
       JBoss Messaging will be the default JMS provider in later versions of JBoss Enterprise Application Platform,
       and JBoss Service Integration Platform.
       It will also be the default JMS provider in JBoss Application Server 5, and is the default JMS provider for
       JBoss ESB.
   </para>
   
   <para>
      JBoss Messaging is an integral part of Red Hat's strategy for messaging.
   </para>

   <para>
       Compared with JBossMQ, JBoss Messaging offers vastly improved performance in both single node
       and clustered environments.
   </para>
   <para>
       Please see
       <ulink url="http://wiki.jboss.org/wiki/Wiki.jsp?page=JBossMessagingPerformanceResultsPre1_0">this wiki page</ulink>
       for performance benchmarks and <xref linkend="performance"/> on how to generate your own
       performance benchmarks.
   </para>
   <para>     
       JBoss Messaging also features a much better modular architecture that
       will allow us to add more features in the future.
   </para>

   <para>
       JBoss Messaging can be easily installed in JBoss Application Server 4.2 using a few simple steps to 
       remove JBoss MQ and replace with JBoss Messaging. Once JBoss Messaging becomes the default JMS provider
       in JBoss Application Server 4.2, there will be no need to do any manual installation.
   </para>
   
   <para>From release 1.3.0.GA onwards JBoss Messaging is designed for JBoss 4.2 only.</para>
   
   <para>
       The procedure of swapping JMS providers is presented in detail in this manual.
       In <xref linkend="installation"/> we discuss how to install and use JBoss Messaging in a
       JBoss AS 4.2 servers. We cover JBoss Messaging-specific configuration options,
       as well as how to run the build-in sanity / performance tests.
   </para>

   <para>
      This guide is work in progress, as new features will be added to the 1.2 baseline at a very
      quick pace.
   </para>
   <para>
	Please send your suggestions or comments to the
      <ulink url="http://www.jboss.org/index.html?module=bb&amp;op=viewforum&amp;f=238">JBoss Messaging user forum</ulink>.
   </para>

   <para> Permanent Team:
      Tim Fox - Project Lead, Clebert Suconic - Core Developer,
      Sergey Koshcheyev - Core Developer
   </para>
   
   <para>Contributors: Ovidiu Feodorov, Adrian Brock, Alex Fu, Luc Texier, Aaron Walker,
         Rajdeep Dua, Madhusudhan Konda, Juha Lindfors and Ron Sigal.
   </para>
   
   <para>Other thanks to Pete Bennett, Jay Howell and David Boeren</para>


</chapter>
