<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="recovery">
  <title>JBoss Messaging XA Recovery Configuration</title>

  <para>This section describes how to configure JBoss Transactions in JBoss AS 4.2.0 to handle XA recovery for JBoss Messaging
  resources.
  </para>
  
  <para>JBoss Transactions recovery manager can easily be configured to continually poll for and recover JBoss Messaging XA resources,
  this provides an extremely high level of durability of transactions.
  </para>

  <para>Enabling JBoss Transactions Recovery Manager to recover JBoss Messaging resources is a very simple matter and involves adding a line to the file ${JBOSS_CONFIG}/conf/jbossjta-properties.xml</para>

  <para>Here's an example section of a jbossjta-properties.xml file with the line added (note the whole file is not shown)</para>

  <programlisting>
     &lt;properties depends="arjuna" name="jta"&gt;
        &lt;!--
        Support subtransactions in the JTA layer?
        Default is NO.
      --&gt;
        &lt;property name="com.arjuna.ats.jta.supportSubtransactions" value="NO"/&gt;
        &lt;property name="com.arjuna.ats.jta.jtaTMImplementation"
      value="com.arjuna.ats.internal.jta.transaction.arjunacore.TransactionManagerImple"/&gt;
        &lt;!--
			com.arjuna.ats.internal.jta.transaction.jts.TransactionManagerImple
			--&gt;
        &lt;property name="com.arjuna.ats.jta.jtaUTImplementation"
      value="com.arjuna.ats.internal.jta.transaction.arjunacore.UserTransactionImple"/&gt;
        &lt;!--
			com.arjuna.ats.internal.jta.transaction.jts.UserTransactionImple
			--&gt;

        &lt;!--
      *** Add this line to enable recovery for JMS resources using DefaultJMSProvider ***
      --&gt;
        &lt;property name="com.arjuna.ats.jta.recovery.XAResourceRecovery.JBMESSAGING1"
      value="org.jboss.jms.server.recovery.MessagingXAResourceRecovery;DefaultJMSProvider"/&gt;

    &lt;/properties&gt;
     
  </programlisting>
  
  <para>In the above example the recovery manager will attempt to recover JMS resources using the JMSProviderLoader "DefaultJMSProvider"</para>
  <para>DefaultJMSProvider is the default JMS provider loader that ships with JBoss AS and is defined in jms-ds.xml (or hajndi-jms-ds.xml in
  a clustered configuration). If you want to recovery using a different JMS provider loader - e.g. one corresponding to a remote JMS provider
  then just add another line and instead of DefaultJMSProvider specify the name of the remote JMS provider as specified in it's MBean configuration.
  </para>
  <para>For each line you add, the name must be unique, so you could specify "com.arjuna.ats.jta.recovery.XAResourceRecovery.JBMESSAGING1",
  "com.arjuna.ats.jta.recovery.XAResourceRecovery.JBMESSAGING2, ..." etc.</para>
  <para>In actual fact, the recovery also should work with any JMS provider that implements recoverable XAResources (i.e. it properly implements XAResource.recover())
  , not just JBoss Messaging</para>

  <para>Please note that to configure the recovery manager to recovery transactions from any node of the cluster it will be necessary to specify a line in the configuration for every node of the cluster
  </para>
  
  

</chapter>
