<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="examples">
  <title>Running the Examples</title>

  <para>In the directory <literal>docs/examples</literal>, you will find a set
  of examples demonstrating JBoss Messaging working in various examples, they
  include: <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>docs/example/queue</para>

        <para>This example shows a simple send and receive to a remote queue
        using a JMS client</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>docs/example/topic</para>

        <para>This example shows a simple send and receive to a remote topic
        using a JMS client</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>docs/example/mdb</para>

        <para>This example demonstrates usage of an EJB2.1 MDB with JBoss
        Messaging</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>docs/example/ejb3mdb</para>

        <para>This example demonstrates usage of an EJB3 MDB with JBoss
        Messaging</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>docs/example/stateless</para>

        <para>This example demonstrates an EJB2.1 stateless session bean
        interacting with JBoss Messaging</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>docs/example/mdb-failure</para>

        <para>This example demonstrates rollback and redelivery occuring with
        an EJB2.1 MDB</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>docs/example/secure-socket</para>

        <para>This example demonstrates a JMS client interacting with a JBoss
        Messaging server using SSL encrypted transport</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>docs/example/http</para>

        <para>This example demonstrates a JMS client interacting with a JBoss
        Messaging server tunneling traffic over the HTTP protocol</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>docs/example/web-service</para>

        <para>This example demonstrates JBoss web-service interacting with
        JBoss Messaging</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>docs/example/distributed-queue</para>

        <para>This example demonstrates a JMS client interacting with a JBoss
        Messaging distributed queue - it requires two JBoss AS instances to be
        running</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>docs/example/distributed-topic</para>

        <para>This example demonstrates a JMS client interacting with a JBoss
        Messaging distributed topic - it requires two JBoss AS instances to be
        running</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>docs/example/stateless-clustered</para>

        <para>This example demonstrates a JMS client interacting with
        clustered EJB2.1 stateless session bean, which in turn interactes with
        JBoss Messaging. The example uses HAJNDI to lookup the connection
        factory</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>docs/example/bridge</para>

        <para>This example demonstrates using a message bridge. It deploys a
        message bridge in JBoss AS which then proceeds to move messages from a
        source to a target queue</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist></para>

  <para>It is highly recommended that you familiarise yourself with the
  examples.</para>

  <para>Make sure you start the JBoss server(s) before running the
  examples!</para>

  <para>The non clustered examples expect a JBoss AS instance to be running
  with all the default settings</para>

  <para>The clustered examples expect two JBoss AS instances to running with
  ports settings as per ports-01 and ports-02.</para>

  <para>For each example, you can always override the default ports it will
  try to connect to by editing jndi.properties in the particular example
  directory</para>
</chapter>