<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="troubleshooting">
   <title>Troubleshooting</title>
     <para>
      <itemizedlist>
         <listitem>
           <para>Message on logs: AIO wasn't located on this platform</para>
           <para>Possible causes are: 
             <itemizedlist>
               <listitem>
               <para>Linux is not your platform</para>
               <para>Just ignore the message as NIO will be selected automatically or change the journal type to NIO on jbm-configuration.xml</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
               <para>The JBoss Messaging JNI wrapper is not on library.path</para>
               <para>Solution: Make sure you have libJBMLibAIO32.so or libJBMLibAIO64.so as provided on the download package.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
               <para>libaio is not installed</para>
               <para>Make sure you have libaio installed at your Linux distribution. This could be done as yum install libaio1 on Fedora or apt-get install libaio1 on Debian. (Refer to your manual to how to upgrade or install packages)</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
               <para>libaio is very old</para>
               <para>We have been using and testing libaio 0.3.106 and Kernel 2.6. If you have older versions you might need to upgrade or change the journal type to NIO on jbm-configuration.xml</para>
               </listitem>
             </itemizedlist>
           </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
           <para>Low response time even though the CPU and IO seems ok</para>
           <para>Possible causes are: 
             <itemizedlist>
               <listitem>
               <para>You are using short transactions in your system and you don't have TCPNoDelay set</para>
               <para>Make sure you have remoting-tcp-nodelay set to true on jbm-configuration.xml</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
               <para>The journal directory is a NFS</para>
               <para>You shouldn't use the journal over a NFS. Make sure you have direct access to the disk device.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
               <para>You are using Asynchronous IO on Linux and you don't have an ext3 or ext2 file system</para>
               <para>If using AIO, make sure the journal folder is on an ext2 or ext3 file system.</para>
               </listitem>
             </itemizedlist>
           </para>
         </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
     </para>
   
</chapter>