<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="client-classpath">
    <title>The Client Classpath</title>
    <para>In this chapter we explain what jars you need on the Java classpath of a JBoss Messaging
        client application. This depends on various factors including whether you're using just
        core, JMS, JNDI or Netty. We explain what jars are needed in each case.</para>
    <note><para>All the jars mentioned here can be found in the <literal>lib</literal> directory of
            the JBoss Messaging distribution. Be sure you only use the jars from the correct version
            of the release, you <emphasis>must not</emphasis> mix and match versions of jars from
            different JBoss Messaging versions.</para></note>
    <section>
        <title>Pure Core Client</title>
        <para>If you're using just a pure JBoss Messaging core client (i.e. no JMS) then you need
                <literal>jbm-core-client.jar</literal> on your client classpath.</para>
        <para>If you're using a Netty transport then you will also netty <literal
                >netty.jar</literal> and <literal>jbm-transports.jar</literal>.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>JMS Client</title>
        <para>If you're using JMS on the client side, then you will need <literal
                >jbm-core-client.jar</literal>, <literal>jbm-jms-client.jar</literal> and <literal
                >jbm-jms-api.jar</literal>. Note that <literal>jbm-jms-api.jar</literal> just
            contains Java EE API interface classes needed for the <literal>javax.jms.*</literal>
            classes, so if you already have a jar with these interface classes on your classpath you
            won't need it.</para>
        <para>If you're using a Netty transport then you will also netty <literal
                >netty.jar</literal> and <literal>jbm-transports.jar</literal>.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>JNDI</title>
        <para>If you're looking up JNDI objects from the JNDI server co-located with the JBoss
            Messaging standalone server you'll also need the jar <literal>jnp-client.jar</literal>
            jar on your client classpath as well as any other jars mentioned previously.</para>
    </section>
</chapter>
