<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="ha">
    <title>High Availability and Failover</title>
    <para>We define high availability as the <emphasis>ability for the system to continue
            functioning after failure of one or more of the servers</emphasis>. A part of high
        availability is <emphasis>failover</emphasis> which we define as the <emphasis>ability for
            client connections to migrate from one server to another in event of server failure so
            client applications can continue to operate</emphasis>.</para>
    <para>JBoss Messaging provides high availability by replicating servers in pairs. It also
        provides both 100% transparent client failover and application-level client failover.</para>
    <section>
        <title>Server replication</title>
        <para>JBoss Messaging allows pairs of servers to be linked together as <emphasis>live -
                backup</emphasis> pairs. In this release there is a single backup server for each
            live server. Backup servers are not operational until failover occurs. In later releases
            we will be supporting replication onto multiple backup servers and active - active
            replication where both live and backup servers operate as active servers.</para>
        <para>When a <emphasis>live - backup</emphasis> pair is configured, JBoss Messaging ensures
            that the live server state is replicated to the backup server. Replicated state includes
            session state, and also global state such as the set of queues and addresses on the
            server. </para>
        <para>When a client fails over from live to backup server, the backup server will already
            have the correct global and session state, so the client will be able to resume its
            session(s) on the backup server as if nothing happened.</para>
        <para>Replication is performed in an asynchronous fashion between live and backup server.
            Data is replicated one way in a stream, and responses that the data has reached the
            backup is returned in another stream. By pipelining replications and responses to
            replications in separate streams allows replication throughput to be much higher than if
            we synchronously replicated data and waited for a response serially in an RPC manner
            before replicating the next piece of data.</para>
        <section id="configuring.live.backup">
            <title>Configuring live-backup pairs</title>
            <para>First, on the live server, in <literal>jbm-configuration.xml</literal> configure
                the live server with knowledge of its backup server. This is done by specifying a
                    <literal>backup-connector-ref</literal> element. This element references a
                connector, also specified on the live server which contains knowledge of how to
                connect to the backup server. Here's a snippet from <literal
                    >jbm-configuration.xml</literal> showing a live server configured with a backup
                server:</para>
            <programlisting>&lt;backup-connector-ref connector-name="backup-connector"/>
   
&lt;!-- Connectors -->

&lt;connectors>

   ...
   
   &lt;!-- This connector specifies how to connect to the backup server -->
   &lt;connector name="backup-connector">
     &lt;factory-class>
        org.jboss.messaging.integration.transports.netty.NettyConnectorFactory
     &lt;/factory-class>
     &lt;param key="jbm.remoting.netty.port" value="5445" type="Integer"/>
   &lt;/connector>

&lt;/connectors></programlisting>
            <para>Secondly, on the backup server, also in <literal>jbm-configuration.xml</literal> ,
                the element <literal>backup</literal> must be set to true. I.e. :</para>
            <programlisting>&lt;backup>true&lt;/backup>
</programlisting>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Synchronization of live-backup pairs</title>
            <para>In order for live - backup pairs to operate properly, they must be identical
                replicas. This means you cannot just use any backup server that's previously been
                used for other purposes as a backup server, since it will have different data in its
                persistent storage. If you try to do so you will receive an exceptin in the logs and
                the server wil fail to start.</para>
            <para>To create a backup server for a live server that's already been used for other
                purposes, it's necessary to copy the <literal>data</literal> directory from the live
                server to the backup server. This means the backup server will have an identical
                persistent store to the backup server.</para>
            <para>Similarly when a client fails over from a live server <literal>L</literal>to a
                backup server <literal>B</literal>, the server <literal>L</literal>becomes invalid
                since, from that point on, the data on <literal>L</literal> and <literal>B</literal>
                tmay diverge. After such a failure, at the next available opportunity the <literal
                    >B</literal> server should be taken down, and its <literal>data</literal>
                directory copied back to the <literal>L</literal> server. Live and backup servers
                can then be restarted. In this release of JBoss Messaging we do not provide any
                automatic facility for re-assigning a backup node with a live node while it is
                running.</para>
            <para>For a backup server to function correctly it's also important that it has the same
                set of bridges, predefined queues, cluster connections, broadcast groups and
                discovery groups as defined on the live node. The easiest way to ensure this is just
                to copy the entire server side configuration from live to backup and just make the
                changes as specified in the previous section. </para>
        </section>
        <section id="queue.activation.timeout">
            <title>Queue activation timeout</title>
            <para>If a live server fails, as client connections failover from the live node to the
                backup, they do so at a rate determined by the client, and it might be the case that
                some client connections never fail over.</para>
            <para>Different client connections may have different consumers on the same queue(s).
                The queue on the backup will wait for all its consumers to reattach before
                activating delivery on itself. If all connections have not reattached with this
                timeout then the queue will activate regardless.</para>
            <para>This param is defined in <literal>jbm-configuration.xml</literal> using the
                setting <literal>queue-activation-timeout</literal>. It's default value is <literal
                    >30000</literal> milliseconds.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section id="ha.client.automatic">
        <title>Automatic client failover</title>
        <para>JBoss Messaging clients can be configured with knowledge of live and backup servers,
            so that in event of connection failure of the client - live server connection, the
            client will detect this and reconnect its sessions to the backup server. Because of
            server replication, then backup server will already have those sessions in the same
            state they were left on the live server and the client will be able to reconnect them
            and resume them 100% transparently as if nothing happened.</para>
        <para>For automatic failover JBoss Messaging requires <emphasis>zero</emphasis> coding of
            special failover code on the client or server. This differs from other messaging systems
            which intrusively require you to code special failover handling code. JBoss Messaging
            automatic failover preserves all your normal JMS or core API semantics and allows your
            client code to continue 100% uninterrupted on event of connection failure and failover
            from a live to a backup server.</para>
        <para>JBoss Messaging clients detect connection failure by using connection pinging on the
            connection. If the client does not receive a pong response from the server in good time
            after a ping is sent, it will assume the connection has failed and attempt
            failover.</para>
        <para>JBoss Messaging clients can be configured with the list of live-backup server pairs in
            a number of different ways. They can be configured explicitly or probably the most
            common way of doing this is to use <emphasis>server discovery</emphasis> for the client
            to automatically discover the list. For full details on how to configure clients please
            see the section on server discovery [LINK].</para>
        <para>Sometimes you want a client to failover onto a backup server even if the live server
            is just cleanly shutdown rather than having crashed or the connection failed. To
            configure this you can set the property <literal>FailoverOnServerShutdown</literal> to
            false either on the <literal>JBossConnectionFactory</literal> if you're using JMS or in
            the <literal>jbm-jms.xml</literal> file when you define the connection factory, or if
            using core by setting the property directly on the <literal
                >ClientSessionFactoryImpl</literal> instance after creation. The default value for
            this property is <literal>false</literal>, this means that by default <emphasis>JBoss
                Messaging clients will not failover to a backup server if the live server is simply
                shutdown cleanly.</emphasis></para>
        <para>For a fully functional example of automatic failover please see [LINK].</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Application-level client failover</title>
        <para>In some cases you may not want automatic client failover, and prefer to handle any
            connection failure yourself, and code your own manually reconnection logic in your own
            failure handler. We define this as <emphasis>application-level</emphasis> failover,
            since the failover is handled at the user application level.</para>
        <para>If all your clients use application-level failover then you do not need server
            replication on the server side, and should disabled this. Server replication has some
            performance overhead and should be disabled if it is not required. To disable server
            replication simply do not specify a <literal>backup-connector</literal> element for each
            live server.</para>
        <para>To implement application-level failover, if you're using JMS then you need to code an
                <literal>ExceptionListener</literal> class on the JMS connection. The <literal
                >ExceptionListener</literal> wil be called by JBoss Messaging in the event that
            connection failure is detected. In your <literal>ExceptionListener</literal> you would
            close your old JMS connections, potentially look up new connection factory instances
            from JNDI and creating new connections. In this case you may well be using HA-JNDI
            [link] to ensure that the new connection factory is looked up from a different
            server.</para>
        <para>For a working example of application-level failover please see example [LINK].</para>
        <para>If you are using the core API, then the procedure is very similar - you would code a
                <literal>FailureListener</literal> on your core <literal>ClientSession</literal>
            instances.</para>
        <para>For a fully functional example of application-level failover please see [LINK].</para>
    </section>
</chapter>
