<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- ============================================================================= -->
<!-- Copyright © 2009 Red Hat, Inc. and others.                                    -->
<!--                                                                               -->
<!-- The text of and illustrations in this document are licensed by Red Hat under  -->
<!-- a Creative Commons Attribution–Share Alike 3.0 Unported license ("CC-BY-SA"). -->
<!--                                                                               -->
<!-- An explanation of CC-BY-SA is available at                                    -->
<!--                                                                               -->
<!--            http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/.                    -->
<!--                                                                               -->
<!-- In accordance with CC-BY-SA, if you distribute this document or an adaptation -->
<!-- of it, you must provide the URL for the original version.                     -->
<!--                                                                               -->
<!-- Red Hat, as the licensor of this document, waives the right to enforce,       -->
<!-- and agrees not to assert, Section 4d of CC-BY-SA to the fullest extent        -->
<!-- permitted by applicable law.                                                  -->
<!-- ============================================================================= -->
<chapter id="interoperability">
    <title>Interoperability</title>
    <section id="stomp">
        <title>Stomp</title>
        <para><ulink url="http://stomp.codehaus.org/">Stomp</ulink> is a text-orientated wire protocol that allows
            Stomp clients to communicate with Stomp Brokers.</para>
        <para><ulink url="http://stomp.codehaus.org/Clients">Stomp clients</ulink> are available for
        several languages and platforms making it a good choice for interoperability.</para>
        <section id="stomp.native">
          <title>Native Stomp support</title>
          <para>HornetQ provides native support for Stomp. To be able to send and receive Stomp messages,
            you must configure a <literal>NettyAcceptor</literal> with a <literal>protocol</literal>
            parameter set to <literal>stomp</literal>:</para>
<programlisting>
	&lt;acceptor name="stomp-acceptor">
		&lt;factory-class>org.hornetq.core.remoting.impl.netty.NettyAcceptorFactory&lt;/factory-class>
		&lt;param key="protocol"  value="stomp"/>
		&lt;param key="port"  value="61613"/>
	&lt;/acceptor>
</programlisting>
          <para>With this configuration, HornetQ will accept Stomp connections on 
            the port <literal>61613</literal> (which is the default port of the Stomp brokers).</para>
          <para>See the <literal>stomp</literal> example which shows how to configure a HornetQ server with Stomp.</para>
          <section>
            <title>Limitations</title>
            <para>Message acknowledgements are not transactional. The ACK frame can not be part of a transaction
              (it will be ignored if its <literal>transaction</literal> header is set).</para>
          </section>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>Mapping Stomp destinations to HornetQ addresses and queues</title>
          <para>Stomp clients deals with <emphasis>destinations</emphasis> when sending messages and subscribing.
            Destination names are simply strings which are mapped to some form of destination on the 
            server - how the server translates these is left to the server implementation.</para>
           <para>In HornetQ, these destinations are mapped to <emphasis>addresses</emphasis> and <emphasis>queues</emphasis>.
            When a Stomp client sends a message (using a <literal>SEND</literal> frame), the specified destination is mapped
            to an address.
            When a Stomp client subscribes (or unsubscribes) for a destination (using a <literal>SUBSCRIBE</literal>
            or <literal>UNSUBSCRIBE</literal> frame), the destination is mapped to a HornetQ queue.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Stomp and JMS interoperabilty</title>
          <section>
            <title>Using JMS destinations</title>
            <para>As explained in <xref linkend="jms-core-mapping" />, JMS destinations are also mapped to HornetQ addresses and queues.
              If you want to use Stomp to send messages to JMS destinations, the Stomp destinations must follow the same convention:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>send or subscribe to a JMS <emphasis>Queue</emphasis> by prepending the queue name by <literal>jms.queue.</literal>.</para>
                <para>For example, to send a message to the <literal>orders</literal> JMS Queue, the Stomp client must send the frame:</para>
                <programlisting>
SEND
destination:jms.queue.orders

hello queue orders
^@
                </programlisting>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>send or subscribe to a JMS <emphasis>Topic</emphasis> by prepending the topic name by <literal>jms.topic.</literal>.</para>
                <para>For example to subscribe to the <literal>stocks</literal> JMS Topic, the Stomp client must send the frame:</para>
                <programlisting>
SUBSCRIBE
destination:jms.topic.stocks

^@
                </programlisting>
              </listitem>
             </itemizedlist>
           </section>

           <section>
             <title>Send and consuming Stomp message from JMS or HornetQ Core API</title>
             <para>Stomp is mainly a text-orientated protocol. To make it simpler to interoperate with JMS and HornetQ Core API, 
               our Stomp implementation checks for presence of the <literal>content-length</literal> header to decide how to map a Stomp message
               to a JMS Message or a Core message.
             </para>
             <para>If the Stomp message does <emphasis>not</emphasis> have a <literal>content-length</literal> header, it will be mapped to a JMS <emphasis>TextMessage</emphasis>
               or a Core message with a <emphasis>single nullable SimpleString in the body buffer</emphasis>.</para>
             <para>Alternatively, if the Stomp message <emphasis>has</emphasis> a <literal>content-length</literal> header, 
               it will be mapped to a JMS <emphasis>BytesMessage</emphasis>
               or a Core message with a <emphasis>byte[] in the body buffer</emphasis>.</para>
             <para>The same logic applies when mapping a JMS message or a Core message to Stomp. A Stomp client can check the presence
                of the <literal>content-length</literal> header to determine the type of the message body (String or bytes).</para>
          </section>
        </section>
        
        <section id="stomp.websockets">
         <title>Stomp Over Web Sockets</title>
         <para>HornetQ also support Stomp over <ulink url="http://dev.w3.org/html5/websockets/">Web Sockets</ulink>. Modern web browser which support Web Sockets can send and receive
            Stomp messages from HornetQ.</para>
         <para>To enable Stomp over Web Sockets, you must configure a <literal>NettyAcceptor</literal> with a <literal>protocol</literal>
            parameter set to <literal>stomp_ws</literal>:</para>
         <programlisting>
&lt;acceptor name="stomp-ws-acceptor">
	&lt;factory-class>org.hornetq.core.remoting.impl.netty.NettyAcceptorFactory&lt;/factory-class>
	&lt;param key="protocol" value="stomp_ws"/>
	&lt;param key="port" value="61614"/>
&lt;/acceptor>
         </programlisting>
         <para>With this configuration, HornetQ will accept Stomp connections over Web Sockets on 
            the port <literal>61614</literal> with the URL path <literal>/stomp</literal>.
            Web browser can then connect to <literal>ws://&lt;server&gt;:61614/stomp</literal> using a Web Socket to send and receive Stomp
            messages.</para>
         <para>A companion JavaScript library to ease client-side development is available from 
            <ulink url="http://github.com/jmesnil/stomp-websocket">GitHub</ulink> (please see
            its <ulink url="http://jmesnil.net/stomp-websocket/doc/">documentation</ulink> for a complete description).</para>
         <para>The <literal>stomp-websockets</literal> example shows how to configure HornetQ server to have web browsers and Java
            applications exchanges messages on a JMS topic.</para>
        </section>

        <section id="stompconnect">
          <title>StompConnect</title>
          <para><ulink url="http://stomp.codehaus.org/StompConnect">StompConnect</ulink> is a server that
            can act as a Stomp broker and proxy the Stomp protocol to the standard JMS API.
            Consequently, using StompConnect it is possible to turn HornetQ into a Stomp Broker and
            use any of the available stomp clients. These include clients written in C, C++, c# and
            .net etc.</para>
          <para>To run StompConnect first start the HornetQ server and make sure that it is using
            JNDI.</para>
          <para>Stomp requires the file <literal>jndi.properties</literal> to be available on the
            classpath. This should look something like:</para>
          <programlisting>java.naming.factory.initial=org.jnp.interfaces.NamingContextFactory
java.naming.provider.url=jnp://localhost:1099
java.naming.factory.url.pkgs=org.jboss.naming:org.jnp.interfaces</programlisting>
          <para>Make sure this file is in the classpath along with the StompConnect jar and the
            HornetQ jars and simply run <literal>java org.codehaus.stomp.jms.Main</literal>.</para>
        </section>
        
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>REST</title>
        <para>REST support coming soon!</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>AMQP</title>
        <para>AMQP support coming soon!</para>
    </section>
</chapter>
