<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="jms-core-mapping">
    <title>Mapping JMS to Core API</title>
    <para>This chapter describes how JMS destinations are mapped to JBoss Messaging Core
        resources</para>
    <para>JBoss Messaging Core is JMS agnostic. It does not have any concept of a JMS Topic. A JMS
        Topic is implemented in Core as an address (the topic name) with zero or more queues bound
        to it. Each queue bound to that address represents a topic subscription. Likewise, a JMS
        Queue is implemented as an address (the JMS Queue name) with one single queue bound to it
        which represents the JMS Queue.</para>
    <para>By convention, all JMS Queues map to core queues where the core queue name has the string
            <literal>jms.queue.</literal> prepended to it. E.g. the JMS Queue with the name
        "orders.europe" would map to the core queue with the name "jms.queue.orders.europe". The
        address at which the core queue is bound is also given by the core queue name.</para>
    <para>For JMS Topics the address at which the queues that represent the subscriptions are bound
        is given by prepending the string "jms.topic." to the name of the JMS Topic. E.g. the JMS
        Topic with name "news.europe" would map to the core address "jms.topic.news.europe"</para>
    <para>In other words if you send a JMS Message to a JMS Queue with name "orders.europe" it will
        get routed on the server to any core queues bound to the address "jms.queue.orders.europe".
        If you send a JMS Message to a JMS Topic with name "news.europe" it will get routed on the
        server to any core queues bound to the address "jms.topic.news.europe".</para>
    <para>If you want to configure settings for a JMS Queue with the name "orders.europe", you need
        to configure the corresponding core queue "jms.queue.orders.europe":</para>
    <programlisting>
      &lt;!-- expired messages in JMS Queue "orders.europe"
            will be sent to the JMS Queue "expiry.europe" --&gt;
      &lt;address-setting match="jms.queue.orders.europe"&gt;
         &lt;expiry-address&gt;jms.queue.expiry.europe&lt;/expiry-address&gt;
         ...
      &lt;/address-setting&gt;
   </programlisting>
</chapter>
