<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="logging">
    <title>Logging</title>
    <para>JBM uses standard <ulink url="http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.4.2/docs/guide/util/logging/">JDK
            logging</ulink>, (a.k.a Java-Util-Logging: JUL), for all its logging. This means we have
        no dependencies on any third party logging framework. Users can provide their own logging
        handler to use or alternatively use the log4j handler supplied by JBoss Messaging.</para>
    <para>The handlers are configured via the JUL <literal>logging.properties</literal> file. This
        default location for this file is under the <literal>lib</literal> directory found in the
        Java home directory but it can be overridden by setting the <literal
            >java.util.logging.config.file</literal> system property to point to the appropriate
        logging.properties file. The standalone JBM server does this and the <literal
            >logging.properties</literal> file can be found under the <literal>config</literal>
        directory of the JBM installation. </para>
    <para>By default the standalone server is configured to use the standard console handler and a
        file handler that logs to <literal>bin/logs/messaging.log</literal>.</para>
    <para>Because some of the third party components used to bootstrap JBoss Messaging, i.e. the
        Microcontainer, use the JBoss Logging framework we have supplied a plugin class that
        redirects this to the JUL logger. This is set via a system property, <literal
            >-Dorg.jboss.logging.Logger.pluginClass=org.jboss.messaging.integration.logging.JBMLoggerPlugin</literal>.
        This is only needed when starting the standalone server and is set in the run script. This
        is not a problem if you are embedding JBoss Messaging in your own code as the Microcontainer
        won't be being used.</para>
    <section>
        <title>Log4j Configuration</title>
        <para>JBoss Messaging supplies a JUL Log4j handler that can be used instead of the defaults.
            To use this simply edit the logging.properties file as such:</para>
        <programlisting>handlers=org.jboss.messaging.integration.logging.Log4jLoggerHandler</programlisting>
        <para>You will also need to download the Log4j jars and place them in the <literal
                >lib</literal> directory and also provide a log4j configuration and place it on the
            appropriate config directory, i.e. <literal>config/common</literal>.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Logging With The JBoss Application Server</title>
        <para>When JBoss Messaging is deployed within the Application Server then it will still use
            JUL  however the logging is redirected to the default JBoss logger. For more information
            on this refer to the JBoss documentation.</para>
    </section>
</chapter>
