<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="pre-acknowledge">
   <title>Pre-Acknowledge Mode</title>
   <para>JMS specifies 3 acknowledgement modes:</para>
   <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
         <para><literal>AUTO_ACKNOWLEDGE</literal></para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
         <para><literal>CLIENT_ACKNOWLEDGE</literal></para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
         <para><literal>DUPS_OK_ACKNOWLEDGE</literal></para>
      </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <para>The acknowledgement modes all involve sending acknowledgements from the client to the
      server. However, in the case where you can afford to lose messages in event of failure, it
      would make sense to acknowledge the message on the server <emphasis>before</emphasis>
      delivering it to the client.</para>
   <para>The disadvantage of acknowledging on the server before delivery is that the message will be
      lost if the system crashes <emphasis>after</emphasis> acknowledging the message on the server
      but <emphasis>before</emphasis> it is delivered to the client. In that case, the message is
      lost and will not be recovered when the system restart.</para>
   <para>Depending on your messaging case, <literal>pre-acknowledgement</literal> mode can avoid
      extra network traffic and CPU at the cost of coping with message loss.</para>
   <para>An example of a use case for pre-acknowledgement is for stock price update messages. With
      these messages it might be reasonable to lose a message in event of crash, since the next
      price update message will arrive soon, overriding the previous price. </para>
   <section>
      <title>Using PRE_ACKNOWLEDGE</title>
      <para>To use pre-acknowledgement mode using the JMS API, create a JMS Session with the
            <literal>JBossSession.PRE_ACKNOWLEDGE</literal> constant.</para>
      <programlisting>
// messages will be acknowledge on the server *before* being delivered to the client
Session session = connection.createSession(false, JBossSession.PRE_ACKNOWLEDGE);
      </programlisting>
      <para>Or you can set pre-acknowledge directly on the <literal>JBossConnectionFactory</literal>
         instance using the setter method.</para>
      <para>To use pre-acknowledgement mode using the core API you can set it directly on the
            <literal>ClientSessionFactory</literal> instance using the setter method.</para>
   </section>
   <section>
      <title>Example</title>
      <para>The <ulink url="../../../../examples/jms/pre-acknowledge/readme.html"><literal
               >pre-acknowledge</literal> example</ulink> shows how to use pre-acknowledgement mode
         with with JMS.</para>
   </section>
</chapter>
