<chapter id="UG2_gettingstarted">
   <title>Download Software</title>

   <para>
      The official releases of JBoss Messaging are available as a free download from
      <ulink url="http://www.jboss.com/products/messaging">the JBoss Messaging project landing page</ulink>.
   </para>

   <para>
       The recommended download location is the JBoss Labs Messaging Project download zone:
       <ulink url="http://labs.jboss.com/portal/jbossmessaging/downloads">http://labs.jboss.com/portal/jbossmessaging/downloads</ulink>
       We also maintain an alternate download location on sourceforge.net:
       <ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=22866&amp;package_id=157261">http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=22866&amp;package_id=157261</ulink>
   </para>

   <section id="releasebundle">
      <title>The JBoss Messaging Release Bundle</title>

      <para>
         The JBoss Messaging release bundle (<filename>jboss-messaging-1.2.x.zip</filename>)
         will expand in a <filename>jboss-messaging-1.2.x</filename> directory that contains:
      </para>

      <itemizedlist>
         <listitem>
            <filename>jboss-messaging-scoped.sar</filename>
            - the scoped JBoss service archive that contains JBoss Messaging and its
            dependencies.
            <warning>
               Do not simply attempt to copy the archive under a JBoss instance <filename>deploy</filename> directory,
               since additional steps (such as un-installing JBossMQ and various other configurations
               tasks) are required for a successful installation. See <xref linkend="UG2_installation"/> for
               more details.
            </warning>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <filename>jboss-messaging-client.jar</filename>
            - the client-side library that need to be in the classpath of the client that opens
            a remote connection to the Messaging server.

            <note>
                <para>
                This is an important note on the Messaging client jar. JBoss Messaging has an
                extensive tree of dependencies and bundling all right dependencies in one easy
                to use archive, so no wrong versions inadvertently get in the class path is, as
                experience shows, extremely convenient. However, this could cause problems if a
                different version of a dependency is required by the user's client code.
                </para>
                <para>
                If, for example, the log4j.jar bundled with the release causes problems for being
                too old, one could just simply build the client-side class path so a newer version
                of log4j.jar precedes jboss-messaging-client.jar in that class path. This approach
                may work, but is not guaranteed to work, because we did not run the full test suite
                with any other log4j.jar version except the one we bundle with the release.
                </para>

                <para>
                 A list of required dependencies for a specific release can be found in the
                 <filename>build-thirdpary.xml</filename> file that is part of the companion source
                 bundle that ships with each release. It can also be looked up online in
                  <ulink url="http://fisheye.jboss.org">http://fisheye.jboss.org</ulink>.
                </para>
            </note>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <filename>util</filename>
            - a collection of <literal>ant</literal> configuration files used to automate
            installation and release
            management procedures. See <xref linkend="UG2_installation"/> for
             more details.
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <filename>examples</filename>
            - a collection of examples that should run out of the box and help you validate the
            installation. Detailed instructions are provided with each example, which range from
            very simple JMS queue and topic examples to relatively sophisticated use cases in which
            EJBs and JCA JMS ConnectionFactories are involved, as well as clustering use cases.
            The <filename>examples/config</filename> sub-directory contains various configuration
            file examples.
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
           <filename>docs</filename>
            - this user's guide.
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
           <filename>src/jboss-messaging-1.2.x-src.zip</filename>
            - the zipped source directory. The file can be directly installed into and used
            with a debugger.
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <filename>test-results</filename>
            - the output of the functional testsuite, stress and smoke test runs for this release.
            All these files have been generated during the release procedure and are bundled here
            for reference.
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <filename>api</filename>
            - the Messaging API javadoc.
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <filename>README.html</filename>
            - The release intro document that contains pointers to various other resources,
            including this Guide.
         </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

   </section>


   <section id="SVN">
      <title>SVN Access</title>

      <para>
         If you want to experiment with the latest developments you may checkout the latest code
         from the Messaging SVN trunk. Be aware that the information provided in this manual might
         then not be accurate.
         For the latest instructions on how to check out and build source code, please go to
         <ulink url="http://wiki.jboss.org/wiki/Wiki.jsp?page=JBossMessagingDevelopment">
            Messaging Development wiki page</ulink>, specifically

         <ulink url="http://wiki.jboss.org/wiki/Wiki.jsp?page=JBossMessagingBuildInstructions">
          "Building and Running JBoss Messaging"</ulink> section.
      </para>

   </section>

</chapter>