<chapter id="gettingstarted">
   <title>Getting Started</title>

   <para>
      The official releases of JBoss Messaging are available as a free download from
      <ulink url="http://www.jboss.com/products/messaging">the JBoss Messaging project landing page</ulink>.
   </para>

   <section id="releasebundle">
      <title>The JBoss Messaging Release Bundle</title>

      <para>
         The JBoss Messaging release bundle (<filename>jboss-messaging-1.0.x.zip</filename>)
         will expand in a <filename>jboss-messaging-1.0.x</filename> directory that contains:
      </para>

      <itemizedlist>
         <listitem>
            <filename>jboss-messaging-scoped.sar</filename>
            - the scoped JBoss service archive that contains JBoss Messaging and its
            dependencies.
            <warning>
               Do not simply attempt to copy the archive under a JBoss instance <filename>deploy</filename> directory,
               since additional steps (such as un-installing JBossMQ and various other configurations
               tasks) are required for a successful installation. See the Installation chapter for
               more details.
            </warning>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <filename>jboss-messaging-client.jar</filename>
            - the client-side library that need to be in the classpath of the client that opens
            a remote connection to the Messaging server.
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <filename>util</filename>
            - a collection of <literal>ant</literal> configuration files used to automate
            installation and release
            management procedures. See the Installation chapter for more details.
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <filename>examples</filename>
            - a collection of examples that should run out of the box and help you validate the
            installation. Detailed instructions are provided with each example, which range from
            very simple JMS queue and topic examples to relatively sophisticated use cases in which
            EJBs and JCA JMS ConnectionFactories are involved.
            The <filename>examples/config</filename> sub-directory contains various configuration
            file examples.
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
           <filename>docs</filename>
            - this "Getting Started" guide.
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
           <filename>src/jboss-messaging-1.0.x-src.zip</filename>
            - the zipped source directory. The file can be directly installed into and used
            with a debugger.
            <note>
               JBoss Messaging cannot be built using exclusively this source snapshot, which is
               provided for reference only.
            </note>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <filename>src/jboss-messaging-tests-1.0.x-src.zip</filename>
            - the functional testsuite source archive.
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <filename>test-results</filename>
            - the output of the functional testsuite, stress and smoke test runs for this release.
            All these files have been generated during the release procedure.
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <filename>api</filename>
            - the Messaging API javadoc.
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <filename>README.html</filename>
            - The release intro document that contains pointers to various other resources,
            including this Guide.
         </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

   </section>


   <section id="CVS">
      <title>CVS Access</title>

      <para>
         If you want to experiment with the latest developments you may checkout the latest code
         from the 5.0 head branch. Be aware that the information provided in this manual might then
         not be accurate.
         For the latest instructions, check out the
         <ulink url="http://wiki.jboss.org/wiki/Wiki.jsp?page=JBossMessagingDevelopment">
            Messaging Development wiki page
         </ulink>.
      </para>

   </section>

</chapter>