<chapter id="introduction">

   <title>Introduction</title>

   <para>
      JBoss Messaging provides an open source and standards-based messaging platform that brings
      enterprise-class messaging to the mass market.
   </para>

   <para>
      JBoss Messaging implements a high performance, robust messaging core that is designed to
      support the largest and most heavily utilized SOAs, enterprise service buses (ESBs) and other
      integration needs ranging from the simplest to the highest demand networks.
      JBoss Messaging includes a JMS front-end to deliver messaging in a standards-based format.
      Additionally, the JBoss Messaging core is also designed to be able to support other messaging
      protocols in the future.
   </para>

   <para>
      JBoss Messaging will soon become an integral component of the JBoss Enterprise Middleware
      Suite (JEMS). Currently it
      is available for embedded use within the JBoss Application Server (JBossAS), and as a
      JBoss Microkernel-based stand-alone server. Work to integrate JBoss Messaging with the new
      JBoss Microcontainer is under way.
   </para>

   <para>
      The large and vibrant JEMS developer community fosters its continued innovation and
      enterprise quality. JBoss Messaging enables more agile applications in a wide range of
      scenarios from simple messaging needs to an enterprise-wide messaging foundation.
   </para>

   <para>
      JBoss Messaging adds flexibility to any SOA initiative.
   </para>




   <section id="features">
      <title>JBoss Messaging 1.0.0 Features</title>

      <para>
         JBoss Messaging provides:
      </para>

      <itemizedlist>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               A fully compatible and Sun certified JMS 1.1 implementation, that currently works
               with a standard JBossAS 4.x installation and also as a JBoss Microkernel-based
               standalone deployment.
            </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               A strong focus on performance, reliability and scalability with high throughput and
               low latency. JBoss Messaging already exceeds JBoss MQ in a number of measured
               performance metrics. Full results will follow.
            </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               A foundation for JBoss ESB for SOA initiatives; JBoss ESB, due in late 2006, will use
               JBoss Messaging as its foundation.
            </para>
         </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>
         JBoss Messaging consists of two major parts:
      </para>

      <itemizedlist>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               JBoss Messaging Core – a transactional, reliable messaging transport system.
            </para>
            <itemizedlist>
               <listitem>
                  <para>
                     Supports generalized messages (not just JMS)
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para>
                     Enables other messaging protocol façades to be added
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para>
                     Distributed, transactional and reliable
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </listitem>

         <listitem>
            <para>
               JMS Façade – the JMS "personality" of JBoss Messaging.
            </para>
         </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>
         Other JBoss Messaging features include:
      </para>

      <itemizedlist>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               Publish-subscribe and point-to-point messaging models
            </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               Topics that feed multiple message queues
            </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               Persistent and non-persistent messages
            </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               Guaranteed message delivery that ensures that messages arrive once and only once
            </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               Transactional and reliable  - supporting ACID semantics
            </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               Customizable security framework based on JAAS
            </para>
         </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
   </section>


   <section id="compatibility">
      <title>Compatibility with JBossMQ</title>

      <para>
         JBossMQ is the JMS implementation currently shipped within JBossAS.
         Since JBoss Messaging is JMS 1.1 and JMS 1.0.2b compatible, the JMS code  written against
         JBossMQ will run with JBoss Messaging without any changes.
      </para>

      <important>
         Even if JBoss Messaging deployment descriptors are very similar to JBoss MQ
         deployment descriptors, they are <emphasis>not</emphasis> identical, so they will require
         some simple adjustments to get them to work with JBoss Messaging.
      </important>
   </section>


</chapter>
